<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<result is_array="true">
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/mexico">México</a>
        </name>
        <ana>MEXICO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Mexico</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Carmack (1981, p. 44) interperets the <em>Popol Vuh </em>as describing the journey of the K'iche' forefathers from a Chontal-speaking epi-Toltec center on the coast of the Gulf of Mexico, probably in the modern-day Mexican states of Veracruz or Tabasco. The mention of Mexico in the <em>PV </em>seems to support this, saying "[t]his they said among themselves as they remembered their older borthers and their younger brothers, the Yaqui people. These dawned there in Mexico, as it is called today. Thus surely a portion of them remained there in the East, they whose names are Tepeu and Oliman" (Christenson, 231). Tepeu and Oliman are both names of Nahua origin, like Mexico itself. Although the Gulf Coast area would not be placed to the east of the K'iche' area on a modern map, the authors of the <em>PV </em>seem to have regarded it as such. </p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/medicinadetojil">Medicina de Tojil</a>
        </name>
        <ana>MEDICINA_DE_TOJIL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>cunabal tohil</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>A hidden canyon (<em>ewab'al siwan</em>) beneath the mountain Pa Tojil. Given the name "Medicine of Tojil" by the forefathers.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/arenasarrancadas">Arenas arrancadas</a>
        </name>
        <ana>ARENAS_ARRANCADAS</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>bocotahinac zanaieb</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>One of two names for what may be one or two places along the K'iche' forefathers' path across the sea from Tulan to the highlands. </p>

            <p>Colop (página 151, nota 243) explica que "este 'pasaron del mar' no debe tomarse de manera literal. Es una figura para explicar el paso entre determinados lugares que se anegan en la época de la lluvia, o como dice Tedlock (301), 'en efecto, los nombres describen una calzada como las que cruzan lagos o áreas temporalmente inundadas para conectar varios sitios Mayas de las tierras bajas.'</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/piedrasenhilera">Piedras en hilera</a>
        </name>
        <ana>PIEDRAS_EN_HILERA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>cholochic abah</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>One of two names for what may be one or two places along the K'iche' forefathers' path across the sea from Tulan to the highlands. </p>

            <p>Colop (página 151, nota 243) explica que "este 'pasaron del mar' no debe tomarse de manera literal. Es una figura para explicar el paso entre determinados lugares que se anegan en la época de la lluvia, o como dice Tedlock (301), 'en efecto, los nombres describen una calzada como las que cruzan lagos o áreas temporalmente inundadas para conectar varios sitios Mayas de las tierras bajas.'</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/ikoqij">Ik&amp;#039;oq&amp;#039;ij</a>
        </name>
        <ana>IKOQIJ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>icoquih</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>This astronym probably refers to Venus, the morning star and a very important entity in Mesoamerican cosmology. </p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/echave">Echave</a>
        </name>
        <ana>ECHAVE</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>The Newberry Library <a href="https://i-share.carli.illinois.edu/nby/cgi-bin/Pwebrecon.cgi?DB=local&amp;amp;v1=1&amp;amp;BBRecID=137083">catalog record</a> for the Ximénez manuscript describes Escolio 5 verso as “an apostrophe praising the Dominican Order, dated Aug. 14, 1734 and signed ‘Echave’.” According to Ruud van Akkeren, “El mencionado Echave es fray Ignacio de Echave. Aparece por primera vez el 20 de julio 1732 y por última vez el 4 de diciembre 1735.”</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/tema/aquinas">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/St-thomas-aquinas.jpg?itok=aWLgixWI" width="67" height="100" alt="Saint Thomas Aquinas by Carlo Crivelli / Wikimedia Commons" title="Saint Thomas Aquinas by Carlo Crivelli / Wikimedia Commons" />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/aquinas">Saint Thomas Aquinas</a>
        </name>
        <ana>AQUINAS</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Saint Thomas Aquinas was a Dominican friar, theologian, and philosopher who was the most prominent thinker in scholasticism and the father of the Thomist tradition.</p>

            <p>Santo Tomás de Aquino era un fraile dominicano, teólogo, y filósofo quien era el escolástico más prominente y el padre de la tradición tomista.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/tema/ferrer">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/ferrer.jpg?itok=J3y8H6jh" width="80" height="100" alt="Vicente Ferrer, Wikimedia Commons" title="Vicente Ferrer, Wikimedia Commons" />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/ferrer">San Vicente Ferrer</a>
        </name>
        <ana>FERRER</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Vincent Ferrer (1350–1419) was a Dominican priest and canonized saint.</p>

            <p>Vicente Ferrer (1350–1419) era un fraile dominico y un santo canonizado.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/tema/domingo">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/domingo.jpg?itok=toEnsskh" width="71" height="100" alt="Saint Dominic by Fra Angelico" title="Saint Dominic by Fra Angelico" />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/domingo">Domingo</a>
        </name>
        <ana>DOMINGO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Saint Dominic (1170–1221) was the founder of the Order of Preachers.</p>

            <p>Santo Domingo (1170–1221) era el fundador del Orden de Predicadores.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/chamiyajolom">Ch&amp;#039;amiyajolom</a>
        </name>
        <ana>CHAMIYAJOLOM</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>chamiaholom</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Jolom means “head” and “skull” (Christenson 2007: note 631, page 233). Christenson translates the name Ch'amiyajolom as "Skull Staff," because "As emblems of office, Quiché political and religious leaders carry staffs that are often topped with ornate silver cavings symbolizing divine power" (note 237, page 116).</p>

            <p>Sam Colop (2011: nota 82) afirma que "<em>Ch'amiy </em>o <em>ch'amiya</em>, con <em>-a</em> final como inserción vocálica, quiere decir 'vara' o 'cetro', símbolo de autoridad' y de la misma manera <em>jolom</em> "es 'cabeza', pero en este caso es calavera'', el cual nombre será "Señor de la Vara de Calavera", y su par, Ch'amiyabaq, "Señor de la Vara de Hueso."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/kuchumakik">Kuchuma Kik&amp;#039;</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KUCHUMA_KIK</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>cuchumaquic</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 235, page 103) explains the name of this god as: "Kuchuma Kik' (Gathered Blood) is still known by Quiché storytellers as a cruel lord of the underworld who gathers blood shed upon the ground as a result of injury, illness, or violence. This blood is then served to his fellow lords at a banquet."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/tema/pajaro">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/uccello.jpg?itok=1Crc5uoQ" width="100" height="56" />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>animal</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/pajaro">vac</a>
        </name>
        <ana>PAJARO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>vac</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: 45) uses the name of this bird, <em>vac</em>, as an example of K'iche' linguistic features: "Long and short vowels are treated as separate letters in Quiché and should be distinguished when written. The Ximénez transcription of the Popol Vuh seldom makes such distinctions. For example, the word transcribed as <em>vach</em> might be read with a long vowel <em>vach</em> ('my companion'), or with a short vowel <em>väch</em> ('my face')."</p>

            <p>Tedlock includes a picture of the Vac/Pájaro in his edition of the <em>Popol Vuh. </em>This is the picture that has been selected for this entry.</p>

            <p>
                <em> </em>
            </p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/chamiyabaq">Ch&amp;#039;amiyabaq</a>
        </name>
        <ana>CHAMIYABAQ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>chamia bac</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2004: line 3666) spells the name of the god, Ch'ami'ya B'aq, and translates the meaning as "Staff Bone." In his prose translation (2007: note 226, page 101), he adds, "<em>Xbaquiyalo</em>. The likely etymology of this name is <em>x-</em> (lady), <em>baqi</em> (bone), <em>ya'</em> (water/river), <em>lo</em> (perhaps), yielding Lady Bone Water. Tedlock notes that in Yucatec, bak ha' (also “bone water”) is the snowy egret or snowy heron, and thus translates the name as “Egret Woman” (D. Tedlock 1996, 250 n. 91)."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/tema/rabinal">Rabinal</a>
        </name>
        <ana>RABINAL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>rabinal</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Rabinal refers both to a group related to the K'iche' and to their town, which remains to this day.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1104">Fray Alonso de Noreña</a>
        </name>
        <ana>NORENA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Fray Alonso de Noreña, O.P. was the provincial superior (or prior provincial) of Guatemala. His most significant work was <a href="https://archive.org/details/fratrisalphonsiv00alon">a collaboration with Augustinian friar Alonso de Vera Cruz</a> on the practices of various mendicant orders in Spanish America.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1097">Alonso de la Peña Montenegro</a>
        </name>
        <ana>MONTENEGRO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Alonso de la Peña Montenegro was bishop of Quito from 1653–1687, to whom was attributed the <em>Itinerario para parochos de indios, en que se tratan las materias más particulares, tocantes a ellos, para su buena administración</em>.</p>

            <p>According to William B. Taylor,</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>The nominal author, Alonso de la Peña Montenegro, bishop of Quito in the mid-seventeenth century, completed the text in 1663. It went through seven editions between 1668 and 1771 and circulated widely in Spanish america until the end of the colonial period. It is the manual that eighteenth-century curas and vicarios in New Spain were most likely to take with them into the field, appearing frequently in the inventories of property owned by parish priests and in the footnotes of treatises they wrote. …</p>

                <p>Above all, it provided detailed descriptions of the responsibilities of priests in Indian parishes and what they needed to know to meet these responsibilities. Because Indians were perpetual minors, the priests and royal governors were to be their special guardians, and the precepts of the church were not to be applied to them with the same rigor as to non-Indians.</p>
            </blockquote>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1096">Fray Domingo de Vico</a>
        </name>
        <ana>VICO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Fray Domingo de Vico, O.P. (d. 1555) was a Dominican friar who was assigned to work with Fray Bartolomé de las Casas to enforce the reformatory New Laws of 1542. De Vico wrote three works that were influential for Ximénez: <em>Theologia Indorum</em> (<em>Theology of the Indians</em>); a treatise on evangelization in Guatemala called <em>Tratado de ídolos</em> (<em>Treatment of Idols</em>), and a dictionary of the Kaqchikel language. In his own works, Ximénez responded to de Vico's work, occasionally citing it (as in his theological treatises) and often challenging it (as in his linguistic studies).</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1095">Su Majestad</a>
        </name>
        <ana>SU_MAJESTAD</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Though "His Majesty" ("Su Majestad") is a general title for the Spanish king, Ximénez's references to "sus leyes de índías" (escolio 3 recto, line 27) make this most likely a reference to Charles II of Spain, whose 1680 compendium of the Laws of the Indies was the most prominent edition. When Ximénez was compiling this manuscript (1701–1702), Charles II had only just abdicated to Philip V, and the transition was a long enough process (both politically and in terms of transatlantic news dissemination) that the reference is somewhat ambiguous.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1093">Fray Juan de San José</a>
        </name>
        <ana>FRAY_JUAN_DE_SAN_JOSE</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Fray Juan de San José seems to have been one of Ximénez's mentors in Guatemala. Amid this discussion of how to handle the possible demonic dangers in K'iche' celebrations, Ximénez mentions his advise: "me lo aconsejo así un Relígíoso docto, y de exemplar vída, q'auía gastado muchos aS. admínístrando índíos q'murío ya decrepíto llamado el R. Pe. fr. Juo.-de S. Joseph demí sagrado hauíto."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1092">Antonio de Remesal</a>
        </name>
        <ana>REMESAL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Fray Antonio de Remesal, O.P. (1570–1619) era un fraile dominico y cronista de Centroamérica. Escribió una historia de la provincia de Chiapas y Guatemala en 1619 citada por Ximénez en sus Escolios.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/node/1090">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Juan_Gine%CC%81s_de_Sepu%CC%81lveda.jpg?itok=s5hoeKAf" width="61" height="100" alt="Retrato de Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda, 1791." title="Retrato de Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda, 1791. Wikimedia Commons." />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1090">Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda</a>
        </name>
        <ana>SEPULVEDA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Juan Ginés de Sepúlveda (1494–1573) was a theologian and philosopher. He famously debated Bartolomé de las Casas at Valladolid, defending the enslavement of indigenous peoples.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/node/1087">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Bartolomedelascasas.jpg?itok=UbM8vF0b" width="77" height="100" alt="Bartolomé de las Casas, Archivo General de las Indias, Wikimedia Commons." title="Bartolomé de las Casas, Archivo General de las Indias, Wikimedia Commons." />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1087">Bartolomé de las Casas</a>
        </name>
        <ana>LAS_CASAS</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Fray Bartolomé de las Casas, O.P. (1474 or 1484–1566) was a Dominican friar. A former <em>encomendero</em>, he eventually opposed the system of forced labor in which he had participated. His works, including his famous <em>Short Account of the Destruction of the Indies</em>, denounced the treatment of indigenous peoples by European colonizers. After a failed attempt at the "peaceful colonization" of Venezuela, he entered the Dominican Order, returning to the Americas as a priest and eventually bishop among the Maya in Guatemala. He was instrumental in the passage of the New Laws in 1542, which nominally if not particularly effectively reformed the <em>encomienda</em> system and gave certain protections to indigenous peoples. In 1547, he returned permanently to Spain, where he continued to advocate for indigenous peoples at court and in the Church.</p>

            <p>Fray Bartolomé de las Casas, O.P. (1474 o 1484–1566) era un fraile dominico. Había sido encomendero, pero eventualmente se opuso del sistema de labor forzado en que había participado. Sus obras, incluyendo a su famosa <em>Brevísima relación de la destrucción de las Indias</em>, denunciaron al tratamiento de los indígenas por los conquistadores. Después del fracaso de su intento de "colonizar pacíficamente" a Venezuela, se juntó al orden dominico, y volvió a las Américas como cura y eventualmente obispo de los maya en Guatemala. Era clave en la institución de las Leyes Nuevas en 1542, que técnicamente, si no efectivamente, reformaron al sistema de encomienda y protegieron en cierto modo a los indígenas. Volvió permanentemente a España en 1547, y terminó su vida como abogado para los indígenas en la corte española y en la Iglesia.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1085">Apóstol Santiago</a>
        </name>
        <ana>SANTIAGO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Saint James the Greater, so called as to distinguish him from the other apostle named Saint James, was an apostle of Jesus. According to tradition, he went on mission to what is now Spain, where he is now buried at Santiago de Compostela in Galicia.</p>

            <p>Santiago el Mayor, llamado así para distinguirse del otro apóstol que se llama Santiago, era un apóstol de Jesucristo. Según la tradición, era misionero en lo que ahora es España, donde está enterrado en Santiago de Compostela en Galicia.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1083">Jun Tijax</a>
        </name>
        <ana>JUN_TIJAX</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>huntíhax</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>According to Ruud van Akkeren, "Jun Tijax," or "One Flintknife," is a name of the god Tojil. He characterizes Tojil as "essentially a god of sacrifice" who "may appear as a sacrificial knife." According to Ximénez, he had been equated with Saint Paul the Apostle.</p>

            <p>Citing Ximénez, Ruud van Akkeren attributes this equivalence to the figures' similar iconography: "The Toj of Rab’inal chose San Pablo as their new patron saint because he carried a sword in his hand, which is confirmed by Ximénez who writes that San Pablo was known as Jun Tijax."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1081">San Juan Bautista</a>
        </name>
        <ana>SAN_JUAN_BAUTISTA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Saint John the Baptist was a prophet and a preacher, and the cousin of Jesus Christ.</p>

            <p>San Juan Bautista era un profeta y un predicador, y el primo de Jesucristo.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1079">Xōchiquetzal</a>
        </name>
        <ana>XOCHIQUETZAL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>The Nahua goddess Xōchiquetzal was the mother of Quetzalcoatl. Ximénez equates Xōchiquetzal with the Maya goddess Ixkik'. He further states that his predecessors had, in his view, erroneously equated both goddesses with the Christian figure of Mary, the mother of God.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>lugar</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1078">Guatemala</a>
        </name>
        <ana>GUATEMALA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>The "Kingdom of Guatemala" (which Ximénez refers to as "Reyno de Gualta.") was an administrative division of the Spanish Empire, officially established in 1609.</p>

            <p>El "Reino de Guatemala" (que Ximénez escribe como "Reyno de Gualta.") era una división administrativa del Imperio Español, oficialmente establecido en 1609.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1076">María</a>
        </name>
        <ana>MARIA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Mary, whom Ximénez refers to as "SSma." (<em>Santíssima</em>, Most Holy) or "Ma. SSma." (<em>Madre Santíssima</em>, Most Holy Mother), is the human mother of Jesus Christ. She is also known as the "Blessed Virgin Mary," having conceived Jesus of the Holy Spirit.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1074">Satanás</a>
        </name>
        <ana>SATANAS</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>In Catholicism, Satan is a being who tempts humans to sin against God. As a demon, he is characterized as an angel (that is, an entirely spiritual, not physical, creature) who rebelled against God. Ximénez refers to him interchangeably as "la bestia infernal," "Satanas," and most frequently, "el demonío."</p>

            <p>En el catolicismo, Satanás es un ser que tenta a los humanos a pecar contra Dios. Como un demonio, se caracteriza como un ángel (es decir, un ser creado totalmente espiritual sin cuerpo físico) quien se rebeló contra Dios. Ximénez refiere a él como "la bestia infernal," "Satanas," y más frecuentemente, "el demonío."</p>

            <p>
                <em>Please note that our use of the label "deidad" applies to supernatural agents in general.</em>
            </p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1073">San Pablo</a>
        </name>
        <ana>SAN_PABLO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Saint Paul the Apostle was an apostle of Christ in first-century Asia Minor and Europe. Of the 27 books of the New Testament, 14 are attributed to him.</p>

            <p>San Pablo el Apóstol era un apóstol de Cristo en Asia Menor y Europa en el primer siglo. De los 27 libros en el Nuevo Testamento, se atribuyen 14 a él.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1071">Espíritu Santo</a>
        </name>
        <ana>ESPIRITU_SANTO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Ximénez refers to the Holy Spirit as "el espíritu Sto.," "el espíritu de Díos" or "la tercera persona de la Santísima Trinidad." The Holy Spirit is characterized as the creative force of God in the biblical text of Genesis, which Ximénez compares to the creation account that begins the <em>Popol Vuh</em>.</p>

            <p>In Christianity, the Holy Spirit is the third Person of the Trinity. The Catholic statement of faith, or Nicene Creed, says of the Holy Spirit:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>I believe in the Holy Spirit, the Lord, the giver of life,<br />
who proceeds from the Father and the Son,<br />
who with the Father and the Son is adored and glorified,<br />
who has spoken through the prophets.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>En el cristianismo, el Espíritu Santo es la tercera persona de la Trinidad. La profesión de la fe católica dice de él:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Creo en el Espíritu Santo,<br />
Señor y dador de vida,<br />
que procede del Padre y del Hijo,<br />
que con el Padre y el Hijo recibe<br />
una misma adoración y gloria,<br />
y que habló por los profetas.</p>
            </blockquote>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/node/1069">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/402px-Cristo_crucificado.jpg?itok=aF-7tHGS" width="67" height="100" alt="Cristo crucificado, de Diego Velázquez, c. 1632" title="Cristo crucificado, de Diego Velázquez, c. 1632. Wikimedia Commons." />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1069">Jesucristo</a>
        </name>
        <ana>JESUCRISTO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Ximénez uses the abbreviation "Xpto." for "Cristo" or "Christ," originating in the Greek word "<em>Χριστός</em>" ("Christós").</p>

            <p>In Christianity, Jesus Christ is the son of God and redeemer of humanity. The Catholic statement of belief professed by this text's author, Francisco Ximénez, reads:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>I believe in one Lord Jesus Christ,<br />
the Only Begotten Son of God,<br />
born of the Father before all ages.<br />
God from God, Light from Light,<br />
true God from true God,<br />
begotten, not made, consubstantial with the Father;<br />
through him all things were made.<br />
For us men and for our salvation<br />
he came down from heaven,<br />
and by the Holy Spirit was incarnate of the Virgin Mary,<br />
and became man.<br />
For our sake he was crucified under Pontius Pilate,<br />
he suffered death and was buried,<br />
and rose again on the third day<br />
in accordance with the Scriptures.<br />
He ascended into heaven<br />
and is seated at the right hand of the Father.<br />
He will come again in glory<br />
to judge the living and the dead<br />
and his kingdom will have no end.</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>En el cristianismo, Jesucristo es el hijo de Dios y el redentor de la humanidad. La profesión de la fe católica, apoyada por el autor de este texto, Fray Francisco Ximénez, dice:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>Creo en un solo Señor, Jesucristo,<br />
Hijo único de Dios,<br />
nacido del Padre antes de todos los<br />
siglos: Dios de Dios, Luz de Luz,<br />
Dios verdadero de Dios verdadero,<br />
engendrado, no creado,<br />
de la misma naturaleza del Padre,<br />
por quien todo fue hecho;<br />
que por nosotros, los hombres, y<br />
por nuestra salvación bajó del cielo,<br />
y por obra del Espíritu Santo se<br />
encarnó de María, la Virgen, y se<br />
hizo hombre;<br />
y por nuestra causa fue crucificado<br />
en tiempos de Poncio Pilato;<br />
padeció<br />
y fue sepultado,<br />
y resucitó al tercer día, según las<br />
Escrituras,<br />
y subió al cielo,<br />
y está sentado a la derecha del Padre;<br />
y de nuevo vendrá con gloria para<br />
juzgar a vivos y muertos,<br />
y su reino no tendrá fin.</p>
            </blockquote>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1068">Dios</a>
        </name>
        <ana>DIOS</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>God is the sole deity in Christian theology (among others), in which he consists in a Trinity of three Persons: Father, Son (or Jesus Christ), and Holy Spirit.</p>

            <p>The compiler of the <em>Popol Vuh</em> manuscript, Fray Francisco Ximénez, was a Catholic priest. Catholic beliefs on God are summarized in the religion's statement of faith, also known as the <a href="http://www.usccb.org/beliefs-and-teachings/what-we-believe/index.cfm">Credo or Nicene Creed</a>.</p>

            <p>Dios es la única deidad en la teología cristiana (entre otras), en la cual consiste en una Trinidad de tres Personas: Padre, Hijo (o Jesucristo), y el Espíritu Santo.</p>

            <p>El compilador del manuscrito del <em>Popol Vuh</em>, Fray Francisco Ximénez, era un sacerdote católico. Las creencias católicas sobre Dios se puede encontrar resumidos en su profesión de fe, mejor conocida como el <a href="http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism_sp/p1s1c3a2_sp.html#El credo">Credo o el Credo Niceno</a>.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/node/1067">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/carlos%20v.jpg?itok=vQemdgsh" width="83" height="100" alt="Charles V, painted by Titian" title="Charles V, painted by Titian, Wikimedia Commons." />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1067">Carlos V</a>
        </name>
        <ana>CARLOS_V</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Charles V (1500–1558) was the ruler of the Spanish Empire from 1516–1556, the Holy Roman Empire from 1519–1556, and the Habsburg Netherlands from 1506–1555.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/node/1066">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/hispaniola.png?itok=w8Msjsd_" width="100" height="100" alt="Hispaniola" title="Hispaniola. Wikimedia Commons." />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1066">La isla española</a>
        </name>
        <ana>LA_ISLA_ESPANOLA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>"La isla española" (the Spanish island), today known as Hispaniola (its Latin name), is a Caribbean island shared by the nations of Haiti and the Dominican Republic.</p>

            <p>"La isla española," hoy conocido como La Española (en castellano) o Hispaniola (en latín), es una isla caribeña compartida por las naciones de Haití y la República Dominicana.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/node/1065">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Peter_Apian.png?itok=CTsCz_y6" width="62" height="100" alt="Petrus Apianus (1495–1552)" title="Petrus Apianus (1495–1552). Wikimedia Commons." />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1065">Pedro Apiano</a>
        </name>
        <ana>PEDRO_APIANO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Petrus Apianus, o Pedro Apiano (1495–1552), citado por Ximénez como el "cosmógrafo de el emperador Carlos quinto," era un cartógrafo y matemático alemán. Apianus dedicó su obra maestra, <em>Astronomicum Caesareum</em>, al emperador. Ximénez hace referencia a su <em>Liber cosmographicus</em>, mejor conocido como <em>Cosmographia de Petrus Apianus</em>, que se publicó en 1524 y pasó por muchas ediciones en los siglos siguientes.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/node/1063">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Seal_of_the_Dominican_Order.png?itok=oUfSML_L" width="100" height="100" alt="Seal of the Order of Preachers" title="Seal of the Order of Preachers. Wikimedia Commons." />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>linaje</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1063">Orden de Predicadores</a>
        </name>
        <ana>ORDEN_DE_PREDICADORES</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>The Order of Preachers (also known as the Dominican Order, and whose members are commonly called<em> </em>Dominicans or <em>dominicos</em>) is a Catholic religious order founded by Santo Domingo de Guzmán during the Albigensian Crusade and approved by Pope Honorius III in 1216. The order's charism, or main focus, historically centers around intellectual and educational activity in support of orthodox Catholic teaching. Besides their contributions to theology and philosophy, particularly in the forms of Scholasticism and Thomism, the order's members have played a major role in the legal tradition of the Catholic Church from the medieval Inquisition to the development of international law among missionaries to the Americas in the colonial era.</p>

            <p>Fray Francisco Ximénez, the author of the earliest extant manuscript of the <em>Popol Vuh</em>, was a member of the Dominican Order and undertook his work on the text as part of his order's broader mission to preach Catholicism to the Maya and combat what they saw as heretical native beliefs. Néstor Quiroa writes:</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>"The <em>Popol Vuh</em> serves as a manifestation of the religious encounter and conflicts between the Dominican Order and the Maya-Quiché. The violent subjugation of the Maya population of the highlands, conducted by Pedro de Alvarado in 1524, was followed by their spiritual conquest. This task was bestowed on the monastic [<em>n.b. "mendicant"</em>] orders, namely, the Franciscans, Mercedarians, and predominately the Dominicans or the Order of Preachers. Upon arrival, the Dominicans implemented the method of peaceful conversion first practiced in the American territory by Dominican Friar Pedro de Córdoba. Later, Friar Bartolomé de Las Casas was successful in Las Verapaces, or the true peace, region in the northern section of the country. In addition to learning the native languages and cultures of the neophytes, the Dominicans believed that the information contained in the native narratives could be used by missionary friars to Christianize them effectively. Preserving the indigenous narratives represented for the missionaries an advantage for the eradication of the indigenous religion and the establishment of Christianity, while also presenting a conflict, since it preserved the very thing it attempted to extirpate."</p>
            </blockquote>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen>
            <a href="/node/1062">
                <img typeof="foaf:Image" class="img-responsive" src="http://multepal.spanitalport.virginia.edu/sites/default/files/styles/thumbnail/public/Santo_Tomas_Church%2C_Chichicastenango.jpg?itok=zNXPQRuc" width="75" height="100" alt="Iglesia de Santo Tomás, Chichistenango, Guatemala. Photo by ManfredWinslow, Wikimedia Commons." title="Iglesia de Santo Tomás, Chichistenango, Guatemala. Photo by ManfredWinslow, Wikimedia Commons." />
            </a>
        </imagen>
        <typo>lugar</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1062">Chichicastenango</a>
        </name>
        <ana>CHICHICASTENANGO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>Santo Tomás Chichicastenango, known today simply as Chichicastenango, is a town in the Guatemalan highlands. Fray Francisco Ximénez was a parish priest in Chichicastenango when he compiled the manuscript of the <em>Popol Vuh</em> presented here in 1701 and 1702. Then as now, the population of Chichicastenango is majority K'iche'. Ximénez writes in his <em>Historia de la provincia</em> (folio 1, side 1) that it was in this town that he encountered the "Historias" that we now call the <em>Popol Vuh</em>: "estando en el Curato de Santo Tomás Chichicastenango, hallé que era la Doctrina que primero mamaban con la leche y que todos ellos casi lo tienen de memoria" (folio 1, side 1).</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1061">R.P.F. (Reverendo Padre Fray) Francisco Ximénez</a>
        </name>
        <ana>XIMENEZ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>R.P.F. FRANZÍSCO XIMENEZ</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Fray Francisco Ximénez, O.P. was a Dominican friar born in Écija, Spain in 1666. He is the author of the manuscript known as <em>Ayer MS 1515</em>, housed at the Newberry Library in Chicago. <em>MS 1515</em> includes the text presented here, "Empiezan las historias del origen de los índíos de esta provinçia de Gvatemala tradvcido de la lengva qviche en la castellana para mas commodidad de los mínístros de el Sto. Evangelío," or the <em>Popol Vuh</em>, and its attendant "Escolios." Ximénez compiled the work in 1701 and 1702 during his time as a parish priest in Santo Tomás Chichicastenango. In the prologue, he claims to have transcribed the K'iche' text from various indigenous sources and translated it into Spanish himself.</p>

            <p>Ximénez arrived in Guatemala in 1688 and was ordained in 1689. Besides the text now known as the <em>Popol Vuh</em>, his works include a three-part linguistic study of K'iche', Zutujil, and Kaqchikel entitled <em>Tesoro de las tres lenguas</em> (1701–1704); <em>Historia de la provincia de San Vicente de Chiapa y Guatemala de la Orden de Predicadores</em> (1715); and <em>Historia natural de Guatemala</em> (1722). His writings are based on the knowledge of Mayan cultures and languages that he acquired as a parish priest and administrator over his approximately four decades in various Guatemalan towns, including Santo Tomás Chichicastenango, Rabinal, Santo Domingo de Xenacoc, Sacapulas San Raimundo, and Candelaria.</p>

            <p>As Néstor Quiroa crucially notes, "Francisco Ximénez composed all of his works as a contribution to his order’s objective: to convert the native population to Christianity. Thus, it is not a coincidence that Ximénez placed his 'ethnographic' work on the Maya-K’iche’ religion within an ecclesiastic treatise, nor is it an accident that scholars have chosen to examine his text as if it existed apart from this religious context."</p>

            <p>Ximénez died circa 1729.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1059">Río de Podre</a>
        </name>
        <ana>AGUA_PODRIDA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>puch chi a</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>A river of pus crossed by Hun Hunahpu and Vucub Hunahpu appears in all the translated versions, but not in Ximenez's Spanish manuscript (folio 14r). Both Christenson (Literal Poetic, page 72, note 45) and Colop (page 68, note 96) assert that the K'iche' manuscript's <em>puch </em>is a scribal error<em> </em>for <em>puj </em>"pus." This may have caused Ximénez confusion during the translation.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1058">Río de Sangre</a>
        </name>
        <ana>RIO_DE_SANGRE</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>chiquiquia</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido/>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1057">River Scorpion</a>
        </name>
        <ana>JA_SIMAJ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>ha zimah</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>The river of scorpions is present in Christenson's and Tedlock's translations, but not in Ximénez, Colop or Recinos. The K'iche' reads <em>chupan halhal ha zimah, maui ahílan zimah</em>, which Christenson (Literal Poetic, page 72) transcribes as <em>chupan jal ja'l: Ja' Simaj, Mawi ajilan simaj</em>, and translates as "Into turbulent rivers: River Scorpion, not counted scorpions." Ximénez's translation, on the other hand, reads <em>de allí al agua q’ se trueca; y pasaron donde todo era palos puntíagudos</em> (folio 14r.), and Colop (page 67) has <em>turbulentes y espinadas corrientes. </em>This disagreement is likely due to an ambiguity in the K'iche' word.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1052">Pléyadas</a>
        </name>
        <ana>PLEYADAS</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>motz</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>An astronym for the constellation known as the Pleiades in English and in K'iche' as <em>M</em>
                <em>otz. </em>According to Christenson (page 104, note 198) this word means "to gather together in large numbers." The<em> Popol Vuh </em>states that the Four Hundred boys became this constellation after their defeat by Sipakna, "but perhaps this is merely a fable."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1045">Julisnab</a>
        </name>
        <ana>JULISNAB</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>huliznab</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. According to Christenson (page 96, note 176), "the identity of this mountain is unknown. Edmondson identifies it with Tajumulco, a volcano in the district of Huehuetenango, Guatemala."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1044">Makamob</a>
        </name>
        <ana>MAKAMOB</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>macamob</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. Christenson (page 96; note 175): "Volcán Zunil in the district of Quetzaltenango, Guatemala."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1043">Ya&amp;#039; Xkanul</a>
        </name>
        <ana>YA_XKANUL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>ya xcanul</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. Christenson (page 96, note 174): "Volcán Santa María, southwest of Quetzaltenango, Guatemala. <em>Xkanul </em>is also a general term for volcano in Quiché."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1041">Volcán de Fuego</a>
        </name>
        <ana>VOLCAN_DE_FUEGO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>chicac</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. Christenson (page 96, note 171) translates the name Chigag as "Mouth Fire," and says, "a volcano in the district of Sacatepequez, Guatemala, nineteen kilometers southeast of Antigua."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1040">Pekul</a>
        </name>
        <ana>PEKUL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>pe cul</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. Christenson (page 96, note 173) identifies it with Volcán Acatenango, but cites Tedlock as identifying it with Volcán de Agua.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1039">Volcán de Acatenango</a>
        </name>
        <ana>VOLCAN_DE_ACATENANGO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>hunahpu</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>One of the mountains created by Zipacna. From Christenson (page 96, note 172): "Edmondson and Recinos identify this volcano as Volcán de Agua, also located in the district of Sacatepequez, southeast of Antigua. Tedlock identifies it with Volcán de Acatenango, located in the same district. In either case, it must be a volcano located near Chigag as the <em>Annals of the Cakchiquels </em>describes it as 'standing abreast' of Chigag."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1038">Tinamit Quiché</a>
        </name>
        <ana>TINAMIT_KICHE</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>tinamit quiche</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (page 59; note 7) says: "based on <em>tinamit</em>, a Nahua-derived word meaning 'fortified town, citadel, or fortification wall' (Campbell, 1983, 85). Although in modern Quiché, <em>tinamit </em>simply refers to a town or city, the word is used in the <em>Popol Vuh </em>to specify fortified centers occupied by ruling lineages (Carmack 1981, 23). Here the citadel of the Quiché people is also called Quiché, apparently referring to the heartland region of their nation. This would include the capital city, Cumarcah [Q'umarkaj], as well as its surrounding territory."</p>

            <p>It is perhaps important that the very last line of the <em>Popol Vuh </em>states <em>xere k'u ri mi xutzinik chi konojel K'iche', Sta. Cruz u b'i' </em>"but therefore this was completed now all Quiché, Sta. Cruz its name." This suggests that the initial <em>tinamit </em>reference may in fact refer to Santa Cruz del Quiché, the relocated site of Q'umarkaj/Utatlán, in particular. </p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1035">Uk&amp;#039;u&amp;#039;x Ulew</a>
        </name>
        <ana>UKUX_ULEW</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>cah vlew</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Ximénez also writes <em>vqux vleu</em> (Folio 2r; Christenson Prose, p. 73).</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1016">Santa Cruz</a>
        </name>
        <ana>SANTA_CRUZ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Sta. Cruz</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 892, page 287) helpfully glosses the history of the place name and its role in the Spanish conquest of Mesoamerica. He writes: "Bishop Francisco Marroquín blessed the ruins of Cumarcah in 1539, renaming it Santa Cruz (Spanish: 'Holy Cross'). In about 1555, the Spaniards founded a new administrative center three miles to the east, which they also named Santa Cruz del Quiché (Spanish: Holy Cross of the Quiché). This was likely carried out under the direction of Alonso de Zorita who administered affairs in various Guatemalan provinces beginning in March 1555, including the area of Utatlan. Akkeren suggests that this compilation of the <em>Popol Vuh</em> was carried out in conjunction with the abandonment of the old capital (Akkeren 2003). The resettlement process, which the Spaniards called congregación (congregation), followed a uniform pattern throughout Guatemala (García Peláez 1943, 161-166; Betancor and Arboleda 1964). First, a church was erected at the center of the proposed site fronted by an open plaza, or atrio, for large assemblies to gather for public ceremonies and indoctrination. The rest of the town was organized into squares divided by streets laid out to the cardinal directions. While the new settlement was under construction, families planted their maize on plots the Spaniards assigned to them in the nearby countryside. When the crops were ready to harvest, the older Precolumbian structures were destroyed to prevent reoccupation, and the people moved into their new homes. Christian missionaries staged elaborate dances and festivals to celebrate the event 'so that they would forget their ancient dwellings' (García Peláez 1943, 163)."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>linaje</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1010">Cuatro Casas Grandes</a>
        </name>
        <ana>CUATRO_CASAS_GRANDES</ana>
        <ximenez_quc/>
        <contenido>
            <p>The Lords of the Four Great Houses are Ajtzik Winaq Ajaw, Lolmet Ajaw, Nim Ch'okoj Ajaw, and Jaqawitz.</p>

            <p>With the three Great Houses that preceed them in the text -- Kaweq, Ajaw K'iche', Nija'ib -- the final section of the <em>Popol Wuj</em> reaffirms the number seven.</p>

            <p>In Mayan epigraphic systems, the number seven is represented as a large scroll that passes underneath the eye and curls under the forehead. This image and its numeral signifier is repeated in several buildings of the Dzibilchaltun (Writing Upon Stone) site in Yucatán, most notably the Seven Dolls Complex. Dzibilchaltun is located 21 kilometers from the present-day center of Mérida, Yucatán. For an extensive discussion of Maya numbers, mathematics, and cosmological repetition, see Colin Renfrew and Iain Morley's edited volume <em>The Archaeology of Measurement: Comprehending Heaven, Earth and Time in Ancient Societies</em> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2010).</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1002">Winaq Balam</a>
        </name>
        <ana>WINAQ_BALAM</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Vínacbam</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Escribe Colop (2008: nota 407, página 217): “Comparto el criterio de Edmonson (ibidem) que aquí debe ser <em>Winaq Balam</em> ‘persona jaguar’ en lugar de <em>Bam </em>(que no tiene ningún sentido). Esta traducción conforma un verso paralelo con el nombre precedente, ‘puma.’ Cita a Munro S. Edmonson, <em>The Book of Council: The Popol Vuh of the Quiche Maya of Guatemala</em>. Middle American Research Institute Publication vol. 35 (New Orleans: Tulane University Press, 1971).</p>

            <p>Christenson (2007: notes 885-886, p. 285) translates <em>Winaq </em>and <em>B'am</em> separately, as "Person" and "Counselor/Doer," preserving K'iche' aesthetics of complementarity and balance.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1001">K&amp;#039;oyabakoj</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOYABAKOJ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Coyabacoh</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 884, p. 285) translates <em>Co Yaba Coh </em>(in colonial orthography), and <em>K'o Yab'a Koj</em> in contemporary K'iche', as "Lord Sick Puma."</p>

            <p>Colop (2008: nota 406, página 217) confirma la interpretación de Edmondson, quien mantiene que el nombre <em>K'o Kab'a Koj</em> es un apodo, así formado de <em>K'o,</em> "honorable"<em> y yabakoj</em>, "puma enfermo." Añade que <em>Yabakoj</em> "es también el nombre antiguo de Cuyotenango Suchitepequez". Cita a Munro S. Edmonson, <em>The Book of Council: The Popol Vuh of the Quiche Maya of Guatemala</em>. Middle American Research Institute Publication vol. 35 (New Orleans: Tulane University Press, 1971).</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/1000">K&amp;#039;okamel</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOKAMEL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Cocamel</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Colop (2008: nota 405, página 217) traduce el nombre <em>K'okamel</em> como "honorable mortal", pues <em>k'o</em> significa "honorable" y <em>kamel</em> quiere decir "mortal."</p>

            <p>Christenson (2007: note 883, page 285) translates <em>K'o Kame'l </em>as "Lord Humble."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/998">Wuqub Aj</a>
        </name>
        <ana>WUQUB_AJ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Vucubah</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 882, p. 285) translates <em>Wuqub' Aj</em> as "Seven Reed/Cane," so-named for the "day in the traditional 260 day calendar."</p>

            <p>Colop (2008: nota 404, página 217) explica que el nombre <em>Wuqub Aj </em>quiere decir el "Día del calendario '7 caña'."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/996">Komajkun</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOMAJKUN</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Comahcun</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Colop (2008: nota 403, página 217) afirma que el nombre <em>Komajkun</em> se compone de las voces <em>komaj</em>, "sangre", y <em>kun</em>, "raíz verbal de 'curar'", y de esta forma "probablemente quiere decir médico de los males de sangre." La interpretación de Allen Christenson (citado abajo) indica el contrario, es decir que el nombre del dios significa "no es médico", debido al prefijo <em>ma</em>, o 'no'.</p>

            <p>Christenson (2007: note 881, p. 285) translates <em>Co Mahun</em>, as it is written in colonial K'iche', as such: "<em>Aj Kun</em> is a 'healer/doctor. The m- prefix is a negative marker, which would make the name read something like 'Not a Healer.' As a verb, <em>maj</em> is “to seize, steal, grasp.” Thus an alternative might be 'Seizes Medicine.'" Colop (cited above) suggests the contrary, because he reads <em>Comah </em>(or <em>Komaj</em> in contemporary spelling) as "blood," and <em>hun</em> (here interpreted as <em>kun</em>), as "to cure or heal."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/993">K&amp;#039;okosom</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOKOSOM</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Cocozom</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Según apunta Sam Colop (2008: nota 402, página 217), el nombre <em>K'okosom </em>"probablemente quiere decir 'honorable mojado'".</p>

            <p>Christenson (2007: note 880, p. 285) points out, "The manuscript reads <em>qo cozom</em>. This is most likely <em>K'o Q'osom</em> (Lord Thicket/Bramble/Chaff) The precise meaning of this name is unclear, however, because of the limitations of the Latin alphabet used. <em>Cozom</em> may also be read as <em>Kosom </em>(Fatigued/Perplexed); <em>K'osom</em> (Reclined); or <em>Qosom </em>(Turkey Ruffling His Wings)."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/990">Q&amp;#039;aq&amp;#039; Laqam</a>
        </name>
        <ana>QAQ_LAQAM</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Caꜫlacan</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 879, p. 285): "<em>Kaq' Lakan</em> (Red/Fire Banner)."</p>

            <p>Colop (2008: nota 401, página 217) sugiere que "<em>q'aq' </em>puede ser 'fuego' o <em>kaq</em>, 'rojo.' <em>Laqam</em> 'bandera' conforme Basseta."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/987">Majukutaj Hombre</a>
        </name>
        <ana>MAJUKUTAJ_HOMBRE</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Mahucutah nabe vinac</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 479, p. 184) translates the name of the deity, from whom the first grandfather of the K'iche' line takes his name, as "problematic." As he explains, "Carmack believes that it is derived from the lowland Maya word for 'Traveler,' or 'One Who Does Not Stay' (Carmack 1981, 49). Tedlock translates it as 'Not Right Now' based on the Quiché <em>ma</em>, 'not,' and <em>jukotaj</em>, 'right away/in a moment' (Basseta). Akkeren (personal communication) suggests that the name is derived from the Mam <em>jukotaj</em> (elder, eminent one). Coto lists <em>hu cotah</em> as 'one crown, ring, or similar round object' (Coto 1983, 474). In many highland Maya languages, such as Tz’utujil, the prefix <em>Ma</em> may be honorific, meaning something like 'mister, or sir.'"</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/985">Yakolatam</a>
        </name>
        <ana>YAKOLATAM</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Yacolatam</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: 284) translates the name as "Corner of the Reed Mat," noting in his explanation of Yakolatam Utza'm Pop Saqlatol that the name derives from Nahuatl.</p>

            <p>Colop (2008: nota 355, página 252) indica que <em>yako</em> significa "levantar" en el idioma maya k'iche'.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/982">Ajaw Awilix</a>
        </name>
        <ana>AJAW_AWILIX</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>ahau aulix</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 552, page 198) translates the name of the deity Awilix, after whom the Lord of the Great House of the Nija'ib is named, as “you are watched over/cared for/commissioned.” He notes: "Throughout the text, the Quichés promise to watch over and care for their gods, providing them with offerings, sustenance, and worship (p. 290; lines 8344-8346, 8379-8388). Tedlock suggests that it may be derived from the Kekchi, kwilix/wilix, “swallow” (the bird) and reads the full name as Lord Swallow (D. Tedlock 1996, 297 n. 152). More recently, Akkeren (personal communication) has suggested that the Nihaib lineage originally came from the Pico de Orizaba area, known anciently by its Nahua name Awilizapan. It is possible that Awilix, the patron deity of the Nihaib derived the name of their god from this region and its principle mountain which bore the same name."</p>

            <p>Carmack (198: page 50) cites Edmondson (1965), claiming that Awilix is a shortening of "C'abawil Ixchel," and says, "[l]ike the Gulf Coast peoples the Quichés associated this goddess with the moon," implying that Awilix is female.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/967">Don Pedro de Robles</a>
        </name>
        <ana>DON_PEDRO_DE_ROBLES</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>D. Pedro de robles ahau ꜫalel</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>"Pedro de Robles is known to have taken office soon after 1554, therefore the <em>Popol Vuh</em> must have been written sometime between the years 1554 and 1558" (Christenson 2007: 29, "History of the <em>Popol Vuh</em> Manuscript.")</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/965">Don Cristóbal</a>
        </name>
        <ana>DON_CRISTÓBAL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Don christoual</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido/>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/961">Ajaw K&amp;#039;otuja Undécimo</a>
        </name>
        <ana>AJAW_KOTUJA_UNDÉCIMO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Ahau cotuha</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>
                <em>K'o Tuja</em> means "Lord Sweatbath" (Christenson 2007: note 874, p. 283). The 11th Lord of the Nija'ib line draws his name from the 5th and 8th generations.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/959">Ke&amp;#039;ema</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KEEMA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>queema</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Ximénez originally writes "Queema" as the name (53r), and later changes it to "Quema" (56r). It is unclear whether this change represents a scribal error or a better understanding of how the K'iche' name ought to have been sounded in the Spanish transcription. The word <em>kema</em> translates as "loom," according to Christenson (2007: nota 876, página 283). Although weaving is women's work, and the communication of messages through colors and patterns is a feminine mode of meaning-making, Lord Keema is classified as a male figure in the text: "Quema, as he is called now, was the tenth generation." On indigenous women's literacies, see Susan Kellog, <em>Weaving the Past</em>.</p>

            <p>Colop (2008: nota 398, página 216) observa la discrepancia entre la ortografía del nombre del señor principal en los folios 53r y 56r, pues el fraile Ximénez escribe "Queema" y "Quema." El destacado traductor también apunta que el nombre "antes se tradujo como 'tejido'".</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/956">Belejeb Kej Noveno</a>
        </name>
        <ana>BELEJEB_KEJ_NOVENO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Beleheb quih</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>El nombre del noveno señor principal del linaje Nija'ib, Belejeb Kej, quiere decir el día "nueve venado" en el calendario maya, tal como indicaba el nombre del señor de la cuarta generación, el también nombrado Belejeb Kej (Colop 2008: nota 396, página 216).</p>

                    <p>Christenson (2007: note 873, p. 283) signals that the name <em>B'elejeb' Kej </em>or "Nine Deer" is a "day on the traditional 260 day calendar." The name of the 9th Lord of the Nija'ib generation repeats from the 4th.</p>
                </div>
            </div>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/953">K&amp;#039;otuja Octavo</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOTUJA_OCTAVO</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Cotuha</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>
                <em>K'o Tuja</em> means "Lord Sweatbath" (Christenson 2007: note 874, p. 283). The name of the 8th Lord of the Nija'ib family line repeats from the 5th generation.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/950">Batz&amp;#039;a</a>
        </name>
        <ana>BATZA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Batza</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>"<em>Batz'</em>a proviene de <em>batz'-ja</em>, 'casa de mono', siendo <em>batz</em> 'mono', un día del calendario maya" (Colop 2008: nota 397, página 216).</p>

            <p>For Christenson (2007: note 875, p. 283), <em>B'atz'a</em> is "Thread/Howler Monkey."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>linaje</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/945">K&amp;#039;otz&amp;#039;ibaja</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOTZIBAJA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>cotzibaha</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Según apunta Sam Colop (2008: nota 395, página 216), <em>ko'</em> señala el estado noble del señor principal de los Nija'ib, mientras la voz k'iche' <em>tz'iba-aj </em>significa "casa de la pintura" o "casa de la escritura".</p>

            <p>Allen Christenson (2007: note 872, p. 283) translates <em>K'o Tz'ib'a Ja</em> as "Lord Writing/Painting House."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>linaje</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/943">K&amp;#039;ochajuj</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOCHAJUJ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>cochahuh</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 871, p. 283) translates <em>K'o Chajuj</em> as "Lord Guardian."</p>

            <p>Colop (2008: nota 395, página 216) señala que <em>k'o</em> quiere decir "noble", y que <em>chajuj </em>"probablemente se origina de <em>chaj</em>," término que significa "ocote, pino", o sea "el que enciende."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>linaje</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/939">K&amp;#039;o&amp;#039;akul</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOAKUL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Coacul</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Ko' quiere decir "noble", así es que el título señala la nobleza y grandeza de esta segunda generación del linaje de los Nija'ib (Colop 2008: 216).</p>

            <p> </p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/924">Salmanasar</a>
        </name>
        <ana>SALMANASAR</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Salmanasar</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>"Salmanasar" is the Latin iteration of the name of Shalmaneser V, king of Assyria from 727–722 BC. The second book of Kings details his conquest of the kingdom of Samaria, after which he expelled and deported the population of Israelites later known as the "Ten Lost Tribes" of Israel. Ximénez believed that the K'iche', like other indigenous peoples of the Americas, descended from these tribes. In his <em>Escolios</em>, he writes that the K'iche' "conseruaron algo de el líbro de el genesís, dado q'desçendíesen de las díez tríbus q'en tíempo de Salmanasar, se perdieron".</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>toponymo</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/923">San Anton Ilocab</a>
        </name>
        <ana>SAN_ANTON_ILOCAB</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>S Anton ílocab</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>This is a reference to San Antonio Ilotenango. According to Ruud van Akkeren, "En este pueblo colonial se asentó la rama ilocab [<em>Ilokab'</em>] de los quichés [<em>k'iche's</em>]. Aparentemente, tenían un lienzo que Ximénez pudo estudiar" (218).</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>grupo de deidades</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/909">Hermanos Artesanos</a>
        </name>
        <ana>HERMANOS_ARTESANOS</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>hun batz hun chouen</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Recinos (1949: segunda parte, nota 4) cita la definición léxica del <em>Diccionario de Motul</em>, la cual indica que "Ah chuen, en maya, significa artesano."</p>

            <p>Por su parte, Sam Colop (2008: nota 71) apunta que <em>Batz'</em> es "un día del calendario" y <em>Chowen</em> "es su equivalente en idioma yucateco."</p>

            <p>Los sabios abuelos Jun Junajpu e Ixbaqiyalo les enseñaban "las artes y el trabajo," tal como Sam Colop (2008: 62) traduce la expresión del idioma k'iche' al castellano, incluso las artes bellas (la música, la escritura-pintura) y las artes técnicas (la ofebrería en plata, oro y sagradas piedras preciosas como el jade). Cabe recordar que en el idioma k'iche' el dominio de las letras, mejor conocida como <em>ajtz'ib</em>, abarca toda clase de literalidades gráficas o "escritura sin letra", como así la denomina Walter Mignolo (2003: 319).</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>linaje</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/905">Dan</a>
        </name>
        <ana>DAN</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Dan</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>This “pueblo” of Dan is not found in subsequent translations of the Popol Vuh like that of Adrián Recinos or Sam Colop. In addition, the name is not phonetically consistent with toponyms or lineages in K’iche’. While the origin and exact meaning of this reference is unknown, Ximénez cited Dan’s appearance in the Popol Vuh in his other works as a way of supporting his theory on the place of native peoples in Christian salvation history.</p>

            <p>In the <em>dedicatoria, prólogo y notas</em> to his <em>Primera parte del Tesoro de las Lenguas Cakchiquel, Quiché y Zutuhil, en que las dichas Lenguas se traducen a la nuestra, española</em>, Ximénez lays out his belief that the peoples of Guatemala and Mexico descend from the tribe of Dan, one of the twelve biblical tribes of Israel. “[S]upuesto de que ella provienen todas las tribus deste reino de Guatemala y de el de México, como ellos dicen en sus ‘historias’” (a reference to the “historias” we now call the Popol Vuh), he writes,  the tribe of Dan’s conspicuous absence from the enumeration of the elect in the book of Revelation makes sense. He continues, “son muy pocos o ningunos los que ellos se salvan…no hay duda que es muy especial el modo que Dios tiene en salvar a éstos y muy recóndito al entendimiento humano” (Edición Academia de Geografía e Historia de Guatemala, 1985, folios 3 verso and 4 recto). For Ximénez, it appears that a link between the tribe of Dan and the native peoples of Guatemala and Mexico could explain the exclusion of both groups from salvation history as he knew it.</p>

            <p>It is quite likely that, in whatever K'iche' source Ximénez may have been working from, "Dan" was a reference to Amaq' Tan, the territory of the Tamub lineage in the region settled by the K'iche' forefathers. Ximénez may have assumed <em>Tan </em>to be a corruption of "Dan," or even deliberately altered it to provide evidence for his theory of the Isrealite origins of the K'iche's.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>deidad</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/883">una persona</a>
        </name>
        <ana>UNA_PERSONA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>(Demonium loquens cis) </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: 202) notes that this Latin-language parenthetical aside, which he translates into English as "Demon speaking from here on," represents Ximénez's only explicit commentary in the text.</p>

            <p>In his <em>Literal Poetic Translation</em> (2004), Christenson (2004: 192) adds, "This is a singular instance in which Ximénez glosses the text with a brief comment in Latin, referring to the messenger from Xibalba as a demon, or devil. That Ximénez chose to do this only once and in Latin argues for the overall accuracy of the Maya text as he transcribed it."</p>

            <p>This is supported by Ximénez's own account in his <em>Historia de la provincia</em>, where he claims (emphasis ours):</p>

            <blockquote>
                <p>determiné el trasuntar de <strong>verbo adverbum</strong> todas sus historias como las traduje en nuestra lengua Castellana de la lengua Quiche en que las halle escritas desde el tiempo de la conquista, que entonces (como allí dicen) las redujeron de su modo de escribir al nuestro</p>
            </blockquote>

            <p>For their parts, Colop (2008) and Recinos (1949: 113) translate Ximénez's note, "(Demonium loquens cis) / (Demonío q’les hablaba)" (36v) as "una persona" (a person) and "el mensajero de Xibalbá" (the messenger from Xibalba).</p>

            <p>Como así apunta Sam Colop, "Aquí y entre paréntesis, aparece una inserción latina que dice: 'Demonium loquens eis", lo cual es un agregado de Ximénez dentro del texto k'iche' y que en la columna en español traduce como "demonio que les hablaba". Esta asociación demoníaca por parte de Ximénez debe derivarse de que el <em>Popol Wuj</em> se habla de un personaje alado, como un murciélago venido de Xibalba, lugar que Ximénez traduce como 'infierno'" (nota 232, página 235).</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/880">Kuwatepech</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KUWATEPECH</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>cauatepech </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Kuwatepech es el señor principal de la generación undécima del linaje Kaweq; el otro señor principal de esta generación es Wuqub' No'j.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/879">Wuqub No&amp;#039;j</a>
        </name>
        <ana>WUQUB_NOJ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Vucub noh</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>With Kuwatepech, Wuqub' No'j forms the 11th generation of the Kaweq family, part of the K'iche' community. </p>

            <p>Kuwatepech y Wuqub' No'j son los señores undécimos del linaje Kaweq.</p>

            <p>La etimología náhuatl indica una larga historia de contacto entre el pueblo k'iche' y el imperio mexica. Como así observa Allen Christenson (2004: nota 853, página 277), "<em>Wuqub' No'j </em>(Seven Thoughts) reigned ca. 1500-1523. This is a day on the traditional 260 day calendar, and is likely the day on which this lord was born. His reign was marked by continued war with the Cakchiquels. In the year 1514, two wars were fought, the first at the <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Sotzil,+Guatemala/@15.6281513,-91.1058104,841m/data=!3m1!1e3!4m5!3m4!1s0x858b85af73f7f30b:0x6eee3e05f2a5a6c2!8m2!3d15.6274988!4d-91.103531">river Sotzil</a> and the second at Mukche. The Quiché Magistrate of War (Q'alel Achi) died in the latter conflict and many prisoners were taken. Carmack identifies this lord with Ahpop Tuh, the father of Yaxonkik who was soundly defeated in battle with the Cakchiquels in 1517 (Carmack 1981, 138). The Annals of the Cakchiquels claims that 'during this year our fathers and grandfathers destroyed the Quichés once again; they exterminated them as if by lightning' (Recinos and Goetz 1953, 114).</p>

            <p>In his day, the Quichés also came into closer contact with the Aztecs of Central Mexico. In 1501, the Aztec king Ahuitzotl sent 'merchants and officials' to the court of Cumarcah, likely to demand tribute and/or vassalage. The Quichés ordered them out of their territory (Fuentes y Guzmán 1932-33, 6, 47). Apparently Vucub Noh did not feel as comfortable in his position by 1510, for in that year the Quichés began to pay tribute to the Aztec lord Moctezuma in the form of quetzal feathers, gold, precious stones, cacao, and cloth. These payments continued until the fall of the Aztec empire to the Spaniards (Recinos 1957, 84; Carmack and Mondloch 1983, 142).</p>

            <p>These ties were strengthened by marriage ties. According to the Buenabaj Pictorials, recently discovered by Carmack in the Momostenango area, 'the lord Quiché... wed two of the daughters of Mendectzum [Moctezuma] called Malintzin' (Carmack 1973, 371). In 1512, Moctezuma sent an emissary named Witzitzil to warn the Quichés of the arrival of the Spaniards along the Mexican Gulf Coast. He warned them to prepare to defend themselves (Recinos 1957, 84-85). In 1519, a plague broke out at Iximche: 'First they became ill of a cough, they suffered from nosebleeds and illness of the bladder. It was truly terrible, the number of dead there were in that period.... Little by little, heavy shadows and black night enveloped our fathers and grandfathers and us also, oh, my sons! when the plague raged' (Recinos and Goetz 1953, 115).</p>

            <p>The plague lasted at least until 1521 and, although Quiché records do not mention it, it is likely that it spread throughout the Guatemalan highlands. Edmonson suggests that this may have been an epidemic of smallpox, a disease brought by the early Spanish explorers (Edmonson 1965, 5).</p>

            <p>A similar plague struck Yucatán in 1516: 'A pestilence seized them, characterized by great pustules, which rotted their bodies with<br />
a great stench, so that the limbs fell to pieces in four or five days' (Landa 1941, 42).</p>

            <p>Perhaps in order to present a united front against the Spanish threat, Vucub Noh negotiated peace with the Cakchiquel lord Belehe Qat in 1522, ending the protracted war that had raged between the two nations since the time of Lord Quicab (Recinos and Goetz 1953, 118). This cessation of hostilities did not, however, prevent the Cakchiquels from allying themselves with the invading Spaniards against the Quichés.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/849">Popol Winaq chi T&amp;#039;uy</a>
        </name>
        <ana>POPOL_WINAQ_CHI_TUY</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>popol vinac </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido/>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/850">Lolmet Kejnay</a>
        </name>
        <ana>LOLMET_KEJNAY</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>chituy lolmet queh nay </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Allen Christenson (2004: nota 745, página 255) traduce el nombre Lolmet Kej Nay así: "Emissary of the Deer House," pues "Lolmet (or Lolmay) is an emissary or ambassador.' Kej is deer. Na[y] is the Lowland Maya version of the Quichéan Ja[y] (house)."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/851">Popol Winaq pa Jom Tzalatz&amp;#039;</a>
        </name>
        <ana>POPOL_WINAQ_PA_JOM_TZALATZ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>popol vinacm pahom tzalatz </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido/>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/852">Uchuch K&amp;#039;amja</a>
        </name>
        <ana>UCHUCH_KAMJA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>vchuchcamha</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 752, p. 256): "<em>U Chuch K'am Ja</em> (Its Mother Reception House)."</p>

            <p>Colop (2008: nota 355, página 252) añade que el nombre de esta quinta persona en la línea de sucesión de los Nija'ib significa "asesora" o "consejera de cancillería".</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/853">Ajaw Q&amp;#039;alel</a>
        </name>
        <ana>AJAW_QALEL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>ahau ꜫalel</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>El primer señor principal de los Nija'ib: "U nab'e ajaw," entendido en inglés como "Lord Magistrate" (Christenson 2007: 301).</p>

            <p>Según explica Colop (2008: nota 335, página 251): “El primero de estas nueve autoridades se llamaba Ajaw Q’alel siendo la primera palabra ‘señor’ y <em>q’alel </em>derivada de <em>q’alaj</em>, ‘claridad’, o sea el ‘Señor que ve las cosas con claridad’ o de <em>q’aq’</em>, ‘fuego’, por lo que significa poder. Esto ha sido traducido como ‘Señor capitán’ (Edmonson, 1971: 231) y ‘Señor ministro’ (D. Tedlock, 1996: 185). Carmack (1983: 228), sin embargo, dice: ‘El K’alel era un cargo con funciones judicales.’”</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/854">Ajaw Ajtzik Winaq</a>
        </name>
        <ana>AJAW_AJTZIK_WINAQ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>ahau ahtzic vinac </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 750, p. 256): "<em>Ajaw Aj Tzik' Winaq</em> (Lord Herald Person). Aj Tzik' is a “crier, proclaimer, speaker, herald, announcer.”</p>

            <p>Por su parte Colop (2008: nota 362, página 255) observa que "el nombre propio del (Ajaw) Q’alel de los Nija’ib era Ke’ema y el del Ajtzik Winaq de los Ajaw K’iche’ era Uchaq’ Iboy."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/855">Q&amp;#039;alel K&amp;#039;amja</a>
        </name>
        <ana>QALEL_KAMJA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>cale camha </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Este tercer señor de los Nija'ib tiene un nombre que significa "ministro o capitán", del cual se deduce su importante rol "en función de canciller" (Colop 2008: nota 335, página 251-2).</p>

            <p>Christenson (2007: note 760, p. 256): "<em>Q'alel K'am Ja</em> (Magistrate Reception House)."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/856">Nima K&amp;#039;amja</a>
        </name>
        <ana>NIMA_KAMJA</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>nima camha</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Colop (2008: nota 355, página 252): señala que el nombre de este señor principal de los Nija'ib quiere decir "principal en línea de sucesión."</p>

            <p>Christenson (2007: note 752, p. 256) writes the name Nima K'am Ja as, "Great Reception House."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/848">Nim Ch&amp;#039;okoj Kaweq</a>
        </name>
        <ana>NIM_CHOKOJ_KAWEQ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>nim chocoh cavec </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Whereas Christenson(2003) identifies the ch'okoj as someone "charged with providing the food and drinks for state functions, as well as making pronouncements and public discourses" (269), Tedlock highlights the potentially political play on words, noting that "ch'okoj" places emphasis on the act of sitting itself, thus suggesting that the Totonicapán authors mockingly refer to him as a "Master of Sitting" rather than a "Master of Ceremonies." </p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/847">Ajq&amp;#039;ukumatz</a>
        </name>
        <ana>AJQUKUMATZ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>ah cuꜫumatz </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido/>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/846">Ajtojil</a>
        </name>
        <ana>AJTOJIL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>ahtohil </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>"<em>Aj Tojil, Aj Q'ukumatz</em> (He of Tojil, He of Cucumatz). These are likely priests of the two major patron deities. <em>Q'ukumatz</em> (Quetzal Serpent) was one of the creator deities (see pp. 61, 68-72, 80-82; lines 25, 140-154)" (Christenson 2007: nota 742, página 254).</p>

            <p>Colop (2008: nota 334, página 251) clarifica que "Ajtojil, era el cncargado del culto a Tojil; el cuarto en rango es Ajq'ukumatz, encargado del culto a Q'ukumatz, seguido por el Nim Ch'okoj Kaweq, el 'principal de los maestros de ceremonias de los Kaweq'."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/838">K&amp;#039;onache&amp;#039;</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KONACHE</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>conache</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido/>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/839">Belejeb Kej</a>
        </name>
        <ana>BELEJEB_KEJ</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>beleheb queh</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>El nombre del cuarto señor del linaje Nija'ib, Belejeb Kej, quiere decir el día "nueve venado" en el calendario maya (Colop 2008: nota 396, página 216).</p>

            <p>Christenson (2007: note 873, p. 283) signals that the name <em>B'elejeb' Kej </em>or "Nine Deer" is a "day on the traditional 260 day calendar."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/840">K&amp;#039;oka&amp;#039;ib</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOKAIB</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>qocaib </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido/>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/841">Istayul_Nija&amp;#039;ib</a>
        </name>
        <ana>ISTAYUL_NIJAIB</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>íztayul</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: 283) writes the name of the 7th Lord of the Nija'ib line as "Iztayul." There is also an Istayul or Iztayul who is the 5th generation of the family line of Balam K'onache'.</p>

            <p> </p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/842">Tepepul</a>
        </name>
        <ana>TEPEPUL</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>Tepepul</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Tepepul first appears in the list of Kaweq K'iche' rulers in his association with Iztayul, in the sixth generation. Subsequent ruling generations share his name: Tepepul (who ascended in 1475) and Iztayub form the eighth generation, and Tukum and Tepepul are the ninth generation.</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/843">K&amp;#039;o&amp;#039;akutek</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOAKUTEK</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>qoacutec</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Ko' quiere decir "noble", así es que el título señala la nobleza y grandeza de esta segunda generación del linaje de los Nija'ib, tal como es el caso de su complemento K'o'akul (Colop 2008: 216).</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/844">K&amp;#039;o&amp;#039;ajaw</a>
        </name>
        <ana>KOAJAW</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>qoahau</ximenez_quc>
        <contenido/>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/845">Nakxit</a>
        </name>
        <ana>NAKXIT</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>nacxit </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Described as a great lord from the east, Nacxit is responsible for distributing the signs and symbols of lordship (Ximenez Folio 48V).</p>

            <p>Among others, Tedlock (1996: 315) and Christenson (2007: 241) point to the Nahuatl roots of the name Nacxit, <em>naui </em>("four") and <em>icxitl</em> ("foot"). While both scholars also identify this name as being one of the titles held by the god Quetzalcoatl, Tedlock claims that "Nacxit's 'populous domain,' as it is called in the PV, was probably a kingdom in Yucatán ruled by a lineage claiming Toltec descent" (315). For Christenson, the name's origins suggest a possible reference to "to the extent of his power to the four cardinal directions of the earth" (241). </p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
    <item>
        <imagen/>
        <typo>persona</typo>
        <name>
            <a href="/node/857">Nim Ch&amp;#039;okoj Nija&amp;#039;ib</a>
        </name>
        <ana>NIM_CHOKOJ_NIJAIB</ana>
        <ximenez_quc>nimchocoh nihaibab </ximenez_quc>
        <contenido>
            <p>Christenson (2007: note 254, p. 256): "Great Steward Nijaibs." In the body of the text, he translates the name as "Great Steward of the Nihaibs."</p>

            <p>Colop (2008: nota 355, página 252): "maestro de las ceremonias de los Nija'ib."</p>




        </contenido>
    </item>
</result>
