<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM  "http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/dtd/tei_lite.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Arte de las tres lenguas kakchiquel, quiché y tzutuhil, 
                v.2 Popol vuh; and Escolios a la historia de el origen de los Indios.</title>
                <author>Ximénez, Francisco</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois, USA</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <att xml:id="folio-number">08</att>
                    <att xml:id="side-number">2</att>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>An encoded transciption of the Newberry Library's VAULT Ayer MS 1515, volume 2, Folio 08, Side 2. 
                Based on the transcription provided by online edition of the Popol Wuj hosted by The Ohio State University Libraries at 
                https://library.osu.edu/projects/popolwujs and contained in the PDF document available at
                https://library.osu.edu/projects/popolwuj/pdfs/NotesOnTransPW_Jn_Jl_2007.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="quc">K'iche'</language>
                <language ident="spa">Spanish</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation>
                <date>Spring 2017</date>
                <name>YOUR NAME GOES HERE</name>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="page" n="08.2" xml:id="xom-f08-s2">
                <div type="col" n="08.2.1" xml:lang="quc">
                <!-- K'ICHE' LINES GO HERE -->
                <p>
                    <lb n="1" />nima che v vapalil qui cabal ca – 
                    <note rend="margin-left"><num rend="large">8</num></note>
                    te cut xbe ri zipacna xopon
                    cu chila cuq ri omuch qaholab na qui pa quibano ixqaholab?
xa che maui cacayaco chitele – ba xchinteleh apa copon vi na qui pa vchac chi iqux, xa v va – palil ca cabal vtz bala cha cut ta xuhuruh cut xuteleba cu
10 acanoc, chuchi qui cabal omuch qaholab xata vi catqohe cuq
at qahol qo pa achuch acahau mahabi xqha cut cacachaqui – mah tana bala chuvec chuva – baxic chic hun cache racan
ca cabal vtz xqha chicut ca – tecut xcam quinaoh ri o much qaholab areri. ala hupacha chicaban chire chicacamizah
20 tah rumal maui vtz ri cubano xa vtuquel mi xuyac ri che
cacoto hun nima hul chiri ta cut chicatzac vi cahoc pahul hacama caha vleu pa hul coh – qhata chire chi are ta cut pa – chal p cahoc pa hul ta catarih cahoc ri nima che chiri ta cut chicam vi pa hul, xeqha cut omuch qaholab, ta xquicot cut
30 hun nima hul naht xcahic ta xquitac cut ri zipacna, oh ca– nih chavech chibeta a coto chic vleuh maui cacaxico, xucha
xic. vtzbala xqhacut cate cut xcah pa hul caziquin vloc ta cototahoc ri vleu nahta chi – cahic avmal xuqhaxic ve xqha cut ta xutiquiba vco – tic hul xacu vhul xucoto
40 vcolbal rib, xretamah ri v camizaxic ta xucot cut hun vi chihul chu tzalanem vca
hul, xucoto xcolotah vi caha – nican pala xuqhax cu cah
oc cumal omuch qaholab. quinanucoto ve xquixnuzi – quih acanoc ta chutzinoc, v

                </p>
                </div>
                <div type="col" n="08.2.2" xml:lang="spa">
                <!-- SPANISH LINES GO HERE -->
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>