<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI SYSTEM  "http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/dtd/tei_lite.dtd">
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> 
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Arte de las tres lenguas kakchiquel, quiché y tzutuhil, 
                v.2 Popol vuh; and Escolios a la historia de el origen de los Indios.</title>
                <author>Ximénez, Francisco</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Newberry Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Chicago, Illinois, USA</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <att xml:id="folio-number">07</att>
                    <att xml:id="side-number">1</att>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>An encoded transciption of the Newberry Library's VAULT Ayer MS 1515, volume 2, Folio 07, Side 1. 
                Based on the transcription provided by online edition of the Popol Wuj hosted by The Ohio State University Libraries at 
                https://library.osu.edu/projects/popolwujs and contained in the PDF document available at
                https://library.osu.edu/projects/popolwuj/pdfs/NotesOnTransPW_Jn_Jl_2007.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="quc">K'iche'</language>
                <language ident="spa">Spanish</language>
            </langUsage>
            <creation>  
                <date>Spring 2017</date>
                <name>Rafael C. Alvarado</name>
            </creation>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
<<<<<<< HEAD
            <div type="page" n="07.1" xml:id="xom-f07-s1">
                <div type="col" n="07.1.1" xml:lang="quc">
                    <l n="1">quix, huzuc xtzac vloc, xme –</l>
                    <l n="2">ho vloc, tzam vteleb ta xutzo –</l>               
                    
                </div>
                <div type="col" n="07.1.2" xml:lang="spa">
                <!-- SPANISH LINES GO HERE -->
                </div>
=======
          <div type="page" n="07.1" xml:id="xom-f07-s1">
            <div type="col" n="07.1.1" xml:lang="quc">
	      <!-- K'ICHE' GOES HERE -->
                <l n="1">quix, huzuc xtzac vloc, xme –</l>
                <l n="2">ho vloc, tzam vteleb ta xutzo –</l>
                <l n-"3">copih chi cut hunhunahpu</l>
                ri vvcub caquix xavi vtz x – quibano ma nabe quicha ca – tahic tah rumal vvcub ca – quix. vcaam chi cut veab ri  hunhunahpu rumal ri vu –
                cub caquix ta xbe chi rochoch 10 xa chi cu vlotem veaeate xo –
                ponic. naqui pa mi xcamou. chi – la xqha cu ri chimalmat ri
                xoquil vvcub caquix. na
                qui pa ri ri e caib qaxtoq mi – xiquivubah, mi xzilibatah
                nu eaeate rumal xacachu – iu ahe ve cacoxou chic mi nabe mixnucam vloc chuvi eae cut chixeque vi chitza –
                20 iaba chuvi eae ta cul qui ca ma chic quitzih chi e qaxtoq
                xqha ri vvcub caquix, ta xu xequeba veab ri hunahpu. qui naohinic chic ri huhun ahpu, xbalanq’ ta xquibih cut chirech hun mama qui – tzih zac chic rizmal vi chi mama, hun cu atit quitzih quemel atit chic, xa quelu–
                30 cuquila chic chirihitac vi – nac. zaqui nim ac vbi ma –
                ma zaqui nima tziz cut vbi atit xeqha curi qaholab chique ri atit mama quix– cachbilahtah chibe ta cama caeab ruq vucub caquix
                xa cohtere chivih, quiri ca mam ri cachbilan caminac qui chuch qui cahau quehe
                40 cut que tere co tila vi chi – quih tala quecazipah vi ru
                mal xa elezan vchicopil
                eiah cacabano quixqha que – he curi oh acalab chirilo ri vvcub caquix, xavi oh qoh yavic inaoh, xeqha ri e ca – ib qaholab; vtz bala xeqha –
                
                
                
>>>>>>> master
            </div>
            <div type="col" n="07.1.2" xml:lang="spa">
              <!-- SPANISH LINES GO HERE -->
            </div>
          </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
